<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Pages on Joseph Carl</title>
    <link>https://josephcarl.github.io/page/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Pages on Joseph Carl</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2017 22:34:02 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://josephcarl.github.io/page/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Resume</title>
      <link>https://josephcarl.github.io/page/resume/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Apr 2017 22:34:02 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://josephcarl.github.io/page/resume/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;joseph-carl&#34;&gt;Joseph Carl&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Email: &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:josephcarl7@gmail.com&#34;&gt;josephcarl7@gmail.com&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Github: &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/josephcarl&#34;&gt;josephcarl&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;LinkedIn: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.linkedin.com/in/joseph-carl/&#34;&gt;Joseph Carl&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;about-me&#34;&gt;About Me&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m a Master&amp;rsquo;s student in Business Analytics at Seattle University, graduating this August. I first became interested in analytics while studying applied economics at the University of Minnesota, and knew I wanted to pursue graduate education to improve my analytical skills. Seattle University&amp;rsquo;s program turned out to be just what I was looking for!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of my key skills include data visualization and statistical analysis using tools like R, Python, SQL, and PowerBI. Some of my interests for analytics include using data to understand energy, environmental, and urban issues like housing and transportation, though I&amp;rsquo;m interested in any analytics career opportunity that can allow me to learn and continue to develop my skill set.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please feel free to check out this website and my &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/josephcarl&#34;&gt;Github page&lt;/a&gt; to see some of the projects I&amp;rsquo;m working on. I am looking for data analytics opportunities in the Seattle area, so if you know of any, please feel free to email me or contact me via LinkedIn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;skills&#34;&gt;Skills&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Data Analysis/Visualization Tools: R/RStudio (including ggplot2), Python, Power BI, SAS, SQL, git/Github&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Quantitative analysis: Regression, forecasting, linear programming, and cost-benefit analysis&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Microsoft Office: Excel (including Pivot Tables, vlookup, and Solver), Word, and PowerPoint&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Foreign Language: Proficient in speaking, reading, and writing Mandarin Chinese&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;education&#34;&gt;Education&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Master of Science in Business Analytics&lt;/strong&gt; | Expected August 2017 | Seattle University&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Coursework in&lt;/strong&gt;: Data Visualization, Databases, Data Mining, Programming, Econometrics, and Statistics&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Visualization Project&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Built Dashboard and Visualizations to Show How Californians Use Various Modes of Commuting to Work using R and Power BI&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data Mining Project&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Creating Random Forest, Logistic Regression, and Linear Discriminant Analysis Models to Predict Backordered Products using R
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Marketing Research Project&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Surveyed 50 Seattle University library visitors and analyzed survey data to understand how they use the facilities
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Econometrics Projects&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Built Logistic Regression Model to Predict Mortgage Loan Approval using R&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tested for Wage Discrimination with Regression Models using R&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Bachelor of Science in Applied Economics&lt;/strong&gt; | May 2015 | University of Minnesota - Twin Cities&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Econometrics Project&lt;/strong&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Built Logistic Regression Model to Predict Job Satisfaction using SAS&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;professional-experience&#34;&gt;Professional Experience&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Financial Institution Specialist&lt;/strong&gt; | July 2015 - August 2016&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation | Seattle, WA&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Assisted in identifying inaccurate disclosure of terms and fees on bank deposit accounts, resulting in over $230,000 in restitution to affected consumers&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Interviewed bank chief financial officers, controllers, compliance officers, and other staff to assess compliance with banking laws&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Reviewed banks’ capital, earnings, liquidity, and sensitivity to market risk to determine risk levels and compliance with banking regulations, regulatory guidelines, and internal policy limits&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Compliance Examiner Trainee (Intern)&lt;/strong&gt; | May - August 2014&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Federal Deposit Insurance Corporation | Minneapolis, MN&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Analyzed bank records, including account disclosures, periodic statements, written policies and procedures, and audit reports to determine compliance with consumer protection laws&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Interviewed bank personnel regarding bank products and services to ensure compliance with consumer protection laws, and relayed findings to senior team members and bank management&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Wrote sections of a bank’s Community Reinvestment Act Performance Evaluation report and summaries of violations of consumer protection laws, interviews with bank management, and internal work papers&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Business Performance Intern&lt;/strong&gt; | June - August 2013&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Affinity Plus Federal Credit Union | St. Paul, MN&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Convinced management to implement Popmoney payment service in online banking, providing a new payment option for members&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Surveyed 300 credit union members on their opinions of prepaid debit cards and mobile banking technologies to find trends in their knowledge of and preferences toward those products&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Analyzed various data sets, including loan portfolios and membership details, and wrote reports of findings and data trends for my superiors&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;volunteer-experience&#34;&gt;Volunteer Experience&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Graduate Student Ambassador&lt;/strong&gt; | Jan 2017 - Present&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Albers School of Business and Economics | Seattle University | Seattle, WA&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Accompany prospective students to observe classes for the Master of Science in Business Analytics (MSBA) program at Seattle University&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Discuss the MSBA program with prospective students and provide insight about the program from a student perspective&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Students Against Hunger (President)&lt;/strong&gt; | Jan 2012 - May 2015&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;University of Minnesota - Twin Cities | Minneapolis, MN&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Planned the $13,000 annual budget and presented it to the University of Minnesota Student Services Fees Committee to receive over $3,000 in funding&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Coordinated teams of 10-30 volunteers to pack food and serve at local soup kitchens monthly&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Admissions Ambassadors&lt;/strong&gt; | January 2012 - December 2014&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;University of Minnesota - Twin Cities | Minneapolis, MN&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Provided biweekly campus tours to prospective students and families&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>